A Guide to the Valeriano Weyler Papers 1970.0006
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Valeriano Weyler Papers
1863-1930
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1970.0006
4.5 Linear Feet
The collection includes administrative, military and personal correspondence between Valeriano Weyler and several individuals during his years as a pubic officer of the Spanish Government.
Biography
Valeriano Weyler, a descendant of a military family, was born on 17 September 1837, in Palma de Mallorca, Spain. Wanting to follow the steps of his father, a military physician, Valeriano enrolled in the Spanish Army. In 1853, he enrolled in the Tercera Compañía del Colegio de Infanteria de Toledo (Third Infantry Company of Toledo - Spain) and after a few years he received the rank of second lieutenant. Years later, he entered the Escuela de Estado Mayor (School of the Chiefs of the Army).
In March 1863, he was sent to Cuba as a Comandante del Cuerpo de Estado Mayor del Ejercito de Cuba (Chief of the Cuban Army). The Spanish government was looking for candidates to take military control of the last bastions of the Spanish Empire in Latin America but few wanted to face the risk of yellow fever in Cuba, which was devastating the population. However, Weyler considered this a great opportunity. At twenty-six years old he had the chance to become a commander, while his fellows of the Military School at Toledo were still lieutenants. Once in Cuba, he received the news about a revolt in Santo Domingo and Weyler requested a transfer to Santo Domingo to take control of the insurgents.
Having been liberated, first from Spain (1821) and then from Haiti (1844), Santo Domingo suffered from ongoing attacks of Haitian guerrillas. Since the end of the eighteenth century, Haiti, a colony of the French government, was having constant revolts that threatened the newly independent country of Santo Domingo. In light of this situation, the conservative government of Santo Domingo asked the Spanish Crown to accept them as a colony again. The Spanish Prime Minister, Antonio Canovas, appointed Weyler to end the revolt. The situation in Santo Domingo provided Weyler with the experience to develop his military tactics in a jungle battlefield. The Spanish Military Army decorated him with the Cruz Laureada de San Fernando (Laureate Cross of Saint Fernand), the highest medal of the Spanish Army during a combat, for his efficient handling of the guerrillas in Santo Domingo. In September of 1865, he was appointed as an Estado Mayor (Army Chief) in Puerto Rico, which was a minor Captaincy General.
In October of 1868, Cuba experienced a rebellion of the Creole oligarchy against Spanish domination. The insurrection was lead by Carlos Manuel Cespedes, a landowner, who was supported by the freed slaves of his own plantation. Weyler was sent to Cuba by the Spanish government to fight against the insurrection. This stage of Cuba's struggle for independence continued for a decade, known as the "Ten Years' War".
Later Weyler was appointed chief of the battalion Cazadores de Balmaceda. At this time he wrote about military tactics and new war strategies as well as documenting his theories and views on Cuba war. He was the first military officer to define the Guerra de Guerrillas. Following his appointment with the Cazadores, he was ranked as Brigadier and sent to Port Princess in Haiti.
Years later Weyler returned to Spain, and as soon as he arrived he was assigned to fight in the Carlista War. The Spanish Government recognized his service as demonstrated in the Bocairente Battle, and in recognition of his accomplishments, he was appointed Field Marshal. In 1875, Weyler was sent to the Canary Islands as a General Captain. His rank permitted him to go to the Senate as a representative of Canary Island. Subsequently, he received a lifetime nomination as Senator.
In 1883, he was sent to Baleares Islands and then to the Philippines where fought against the rebellion of Talagos, a native indigenous uprising. When he came back to Spain, he was again appointed as a Captain General and served in different regions of Spain. In Cataluña, he faced anarchist attacks in Barcelona.
Following these actions, he returned to Cuba as a Chief of the Army. This time his mission was to stop the revolt lead by Antonio Maceo. Weyler ruled his officers with an iron hand. To deal with Cuban guerrillas, Weyler instituted a policy of herding the rural population into garrisoned towns, where they could be controlled and the Cuban guerrillas could not recruit or use them for support. His name was synonymous with fear, and this policy caused considerable suffering to the civilian population. Spanish liberals began to criticize Weyler's policies, as did the American press. The United States government identified him as a bloodthirsty commander and asked the Spanish Government for Weyler's discharge. After that, Weyler began to lose ground politically. The situation was exacerbated when the Filipino rebellion drained Spanish troops out of Cuba. In 1897 with the assassination of Prime Minister Antonio Canovas, Weyler lost his political influence. He again returned to Spain, where he died in Madrid in 1930.
Valeriano Weyler is a significant figure in Spanish history and one of the most controversial. Throughout the years, historical opinion has identified him as both a heroic officer and as a bloody and defeated general, particularly because of his actions during his years in Cuba>.
Scope and Content
The collection includes administrative, military, and personal correspondence between Valeriano Weyler and several individuals during his years as a public officer of the Spanish Government. There are letters and documents from governors, missionaries, and other officials in the Philippines. Newspaper clippings, military documents and hospital records for his years in Canary Islands. It also includes manuscripts, typescripts and reports concerning the activities of the Ten Years War in Cuba, the Carlista War in Spain, the Philippine Guerrillas War, and Barcelona disturbance between 1910 and 1913. Moreover, there are also certificates of merit and offices held by Weyler throughout his career as a Military Attaché in Cuba, Santo Domingo, Haiti, Philippines, Valencia and Cataluña.
Organization
The arrangement of the papers is chronological and geographical for all Series. The collection was divided in three series arranged by chronological order. Inside each series it was divided into subseries arranged by the geographical destination of Valeriano Weyler.
Custodial History
Unknown, possible purchase.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Location of Copies or Alternate Formats
Digital reproductions of selected materials in this collection may also be found in the Archives & Special Collections digital repository.
Bibliography
Diccionario de Historia de España. Dirigida por German Bleiberg. Tomo Tercero N-Z. Madrid: Ediciones de la Revista de Occidente, 1968-1969.
Cardona, Gabriel y Juan Carlos Losada. Weyler, nuestro hombre en La Habana. Barcelona, España: Planeta, 1997.
Mínguez, Bernardino Martín. Política y militarismo; defensa del general Weyler, cuestión palpitante y transcendental. Madrid: Impr. de los Hijos de M. G. Hernández, 1897.
Weyler, Valeriano 1838-1930. Mi mando en Cuba (10 febrero 1896 á 31 octubre 1897): historia militar y política de la última guerra separatista durante dicho mando, por el general Weyler. Madrid: F. González Rojas, 1910-11.
- Series I: Administrative and Military Documentation, 1863-1897
  - Cuba, Santo Domingo and Haiti, 1863-1897
    - Cuba
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Cazadores de Balmaceda Battalion, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Cazadores de Balmaceda Battalion, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Cazadores de Balmaceda Battalion, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Rent bills, 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Military ranks obtained in Cuba, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Military issues in Cuba, 1872-1874 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Army section in Cuba Island, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Military issues in Cuba, 1896-1897 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Santo Domingo
      - Operation Army Division, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Puerto Rico
      - Captaincy General, 1866-1867 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Haiti
      - High Court of Army in Port Prince, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - High Court of Army in Port Prince, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Spain: Valencia and Cataluña, 1870-1878
    - Valencia
      - Military promotions and examinations, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Carlista War
        - Operation Brigade, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 24)
        - Telegraphic Dispatch Station, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 25)
        - Captaincy General of Valencia, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - Army of Valencia District, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 27)
        - Pinar del Rincon Battle, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 28)
        - Bocairente Battle, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 29)
        - Telegrams from and to Valencia, 1873-1874 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Captaincy General
        - Military promotion, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 31)
        - Indictment, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 32)
        - Appointments, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Cataluña
      - Carlista War
        - Operation Diary of Cataluña, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 34)
        - Cataluña Army, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 35)
        - Telegrams from and to Cataluña, 1874-1875 (Box 2, Folder 36)
        - Clot de Mala Mata Battle, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Canary Islands, 1879-1885
    - Datum plane, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Captaincy General Accounting, 1879 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Captaincy General Administrative Records, 1879 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Las Palmas Municipality, 1879-1880 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - National Guard Inspection of Canary Islands Accounting, 1879-1881 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Captaincy General Accounting, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Captaincy General Administrative Records, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Provisional Battalion of Canary Islands Accounting, 1880-1883 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Newspaper clippings about Canary Islands Government, 1880-1883 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Pamphlets and Bulletins, 1880-1885 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Captaincy General Accounting, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Telegrams from and to Canary Islands, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Administrative records Ministry of War, 1881-1882 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Captaincy General Administrative Records, 1881-1882 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Captaincy General Accounting, 1882 July - September (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Captaincy General Accounting, 1882 October - December (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Weyler's farewell, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Captaincy General Accounting, 1883 January - February (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Captaincy General Accounting, 1883 March - June (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Captaincy General Accounting, 1883 October - November (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Philippines, undated, 1886-1891
    - Recommendations
      - Residents A - F, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - Residents G - L, undated
      - Residents M - Q, undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - Residents R - Z, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - Officials A - Z, undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - Aspirant officials A - Z, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Civil and Military Government, Spain and Philippines, undated
    - Tobacco General Company, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Captaincy General Administrative Records, 1886 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Captaincy General Administrative Records, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Captaincy General Administrative Records, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Civil and Military Government, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - General Government of Manila, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Philippines, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Consulate of France, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Spain, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Spain, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Civil and Military Government, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Spain, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Codina Company, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Chinese Immigration, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - General Government of Manila, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - General Government, High Court of Justice, Manila, 1889-1890 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - General Government, High Court of Justice, Cebu, 1889-1891 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Spain, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Spain, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Spain, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Civil and Military Government Administrative Records, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Civil and Military Government Administrative Records, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - General Government of Manila, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Philippines, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - General Intendancy of Public Treasury of Philippines, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Newspaper clipping "La Voz de España", 1890 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Civil Guard, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - General Government of Philippines, Recommendations, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - General Government of Philippines, Recommendations, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Civil and Military Government, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Spain, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Civil and Military Government, Letters from and to Philippines, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 96)
- Series II: Political, military, civil and religious government documentation, 1860-1930
  - Philippines, 1888-1891
    - Religious
      - Correspondence (from and to)
        - San Juan de Dios, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 97)
        - Nueva Caceres Bishop, 1888-1889 (Box 6, Folder 98)
        - San Juan de Letran Order, 1889-1890 (Box 6, Folder 99)
        - Capuchins Order, 1889-1890 (Box 6, Folder 100)
        - Dominican Order, 1889-1890 (Box 6, Folder 101)
      - Missions Administrative Records, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 102)
      - Missions Administrative Records, 1890 (Box 6, Folder 103)
      - Missions Administrative Records, 1891 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Political-military
      - Political and military government of
        - La Abra, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 105)
        - Islas Visayas, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 106)
        - Cebu, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 107)
        - Carolinas Occidentales, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 108)
        - Carolinas Orientales, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 109)
        - Floilo, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 110)
        - Archipielago de Tolo, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 111)
        - Cavite, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 112)
        - Tarlac, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 113)
        - Mindanao, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 114)
        - Mindoro, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 115)
        - La Union, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 116)
        - Flocos Norte, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 117)
        - Flocos Sur, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 118)
        - Camerines Norte, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 119)
        - Pangasinan, 1888-1889 (Box 6, Folder 120)
        - Coltabato, 1889-1890 (Box 6, Folder 121)
        - La Paragua, 1889-1891 (Box 6, Folder 122)
        - Isla de Negros, 1888-1889 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Cataluña, undated, 1909-1930
    - Political-military
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, undated (Box 7, Folder 124)
      - Campaign military operations in Cataluña, undated (Box 7, Folder 125)
      - Civil government of Barcelona, undated, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 126)
      - Barcelona strike, 1909-1910 (Box 7, Folder 127)
      - Military Hospital of Barcelona, 1901-1913 (Box 7, Folder 128)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, Amnesty Letter, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 129)
      - Somatenes Armados de Cataluña, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 130)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, Political Letters, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 131)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, Accounting, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 132)
      - Captaincy General of the 4th Region, Accounting, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 133)
      - Infantry regiment, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 134)
      - Military exception of reservist, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 135)
      - Captaincy General of the 5th Region, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 136)
      - Prime Minster Council, 1910-1911 (Box 7, Folder 137)
      - Miltary Government of Gerona, 1910, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 138)
      - Captaincy General of the 5th Region, Accounting, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 139)
      - Captaincy General of the 5th Region, Political Letters, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 140)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, Military and social issues, 1911-1912 (Box 7, Folder 141)
      - Captaincy General of the 4th Region, Diary of orders, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 142)
      - Army Veterinary Corps of the 4th Region, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 143)
      - Captaincy General of the 4th Region, Expenses, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 144)
      - 3rd Brigade of Cazadores, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 145)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 146)
      - Barcelona Government, Telegrams, 1912-1915 (Box 8, Folder 147)
      - Captaincy General of the 4th Region, Accounting, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 148)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, Political Letters, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 149)
      - Barcelona strike, Telegrams, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 150)
      - Barcelona strike, Letters, reports and information, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 151)
      - Barcelona Government, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 152)
      - Alcover and Villalonga revolt, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 153)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 154)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 155)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 156)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 157)
      - Army Chief Staff of Madrid, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 158)
      - Cavalcanty Chief Army Correspondence, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 159)
    - Civil
      - Barcelona University, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 160)
      - Visit to Manlleu Village, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 161)
      - National Lottery, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 162)
      - Compañia de los Caminos de Hierro del Sur de España, 1911-1912 (Box 8, Folder 163)
      - Sociedad General de Mercurioo de Sierra Nevada, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 164)
      - Remonta Nacional, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 165)
      - Special Letter from Madero President of Mexico, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 166)
      - Intituto Agricolo Catalan, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 167)
      - King of Spain's trip to Cataluña, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 168)
      - Movimiento Societario, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 169)
      - Anonymous letter, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 170)
  - Spain, 1860-1920
    - Military
      - Army, Balear Islands, 1860-1863 (Box 8, Folder 171)
      - Army School, 1860-1867 (Box 8, Folder 172)
      - Captaincy General Castilla La Nueva, 1862, 1872-1875 (Box 8, Folder 173)
      - San Fernando military order, 1866 March 16 (Box 8, Folder 174)
      - Military Army, Logroño, 1874 (Box 8, Folder 175)
      - Military Army, War Ministry, Madrid, 1872-1878 (Box 9, Folder 176)
      - Captaincy General of Cataluña, 1889 (Box 9, Folder 177)
    - Political
      - Encomienda Isabel La Catolica, 1870 (Box 9, Folder 178)
      - Gran Cruz de la Orden de San Militar de San Hermenegildo, 1886 (Box 9, Folder 179)
      - Cruz de la Orden de San Fernando, 1898 (Box 9, Folder 180)
      - Bills in favor of Don Pedro Murias, 1898 (Box 9, Folder 181)
    - Printed Material
      - San Fernando Order Statutes, 1863 (Box 9, Folder 182)
      - War Ministry (Madrid), Liquidation of all military corps, 1886 (Box 9, Folder 183)
      - General Administration of the Military Army, Disposition, 1887 (Box 9, Folder 184)
      - Invitation to Junta de Auxilio, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 185)
      - State Session Diary, 1912 (Box 9, Folder 186)
      - Partido Socialista Monarquico flyer, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 187)
      - Representative Session Diary, 1920 (Box 9, Folder 188)
- Series III: Personal Records, undated, 1866-1928
  - Valeriano Weyler's sister, undated (Box 9, Folder 189)
  - Personal Letters, undated, 1887-1888, 1911,1923 (Box 9, Folder 190)
  - Valeriano Weyler's mother's letter, 1866 (Box 9, Folder 191)
  - Personal Letters, 1888 April (Box 9, Folder 192)
  - Personal Letters, 1888 May (Box 9, Folder 193)
  - Personal Letters, 1888 June (Box 9, Folder 194)
  - Personal Letters, 1888 July (Box 9, Folder 195)
  - Personal Letters, 1888 August (Box 9, Folder 196)
  - Personal Letters, 1888 September (Box 9, Folder 197)
  - Personal Letters, 1888 October (Box 9, Folder 198)
  - Sor Maria Asumpta, 1912 (Box 9, Folder 199)
  - Pablo Blas y Pascual, 1928 (Box 9, Folder 200)